Guide to the Bayonne Bridge Historic Preservation Documentation 2007-2021 PR 443
New-York Historical Society
Bayonne Bridge historic preservation documentation
2007-2021
New-York Historical Society
Port Authority of New York and New Jersey
PR 443
.21 Linear feet in one box
2.92 Gigabytes (153 Files, 6 Folders)
The collection includes documentation prepared by the Port Authority for the purpose of complying with certain legal requirements related to the alteration of a historic structure. This includes images of documents from the 1920s-1930s concerning the original construction of the Bayonne Bridge and other material about the history of the bridge. The bulk of the collection is in digital form. All the content of the collection can be found on-line on the Port Authority's website: https://www.panynj.gov/bridges-tunnels/en/bayonne-bridge/history.html
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format.
Biographical / Historical
The Bayonne Bridge, referred to originally as the Kill Van Kull Bridge after the waterway it spans, reaches from Bayonne, New Jersey, across to Staten Island, New York. It is an arch bridge that carries vehicular traffic. Designed by Othmar Ammann and Cass Gilbert, construction began in 1928 and was completed in 1931. At the time, it was the world's longest arch bridge.
In 2019, the Bayonne Bridge underwent a Navigational Clearance Program that raised its roadway 64 feet. This enabled the current, and much larger, generation of container ships to pass underneath, and the Port of New York and New Jersey to remain competitive. It also retained the bridge's principal structural feature – its iconic parabolic arch. It had been determined eligible for listing in the National Register of Historic Places.
In accordance with Section 106 of the National Historic Preservation Act, and in association with both New York and New Jersey Offices of Historic Preservation, the Port Authority developed a plan to mitigate the alterations to the bridge's appearance. Part of this mitigation plan included the preparation of the materials in this collection. The Port Authority engaged Richard Grubb & Associates, a cultural resource consulting firm, to produce or distribute this documentation, which was posted on Port Authority's website and distributed to New-York Historical Society and other repositories in the metropolitan area.
(The above note was based on information from Wikipedia, the Port Authority's website, and the transmittal letter in the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, May 2021.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes documentation prepared by the Port Authority for the purpose of complying with certain legal requirements related to the alteration of a historic structure. This includes images of documents from the 1920s-1930s concerning the original construction of the Bayonne Bridge and other material about the history of the bridge. The bulk of the collection is in digital form. All the content of the collection can be found on-line on the Port Authority's website: https://www.panynj.gov/bridges-tunnels/en/bayonne-bridge/history.html
Existence and Location of Copies
All the content of the collection can be found on-line on the Port Authority's website: https://www.panynj.gov/bridges-tunnels/en/bayonne-bridge/history.html
Related Materials
N-YHS holds several other items regarding the Kill Van Kull / Bayonne Bridge that can be found with a keyword search in the on-line catalog, Bobcat, and in the discovery portal for full-text searches of all N-YHS finding aids. Included in the latter is N-YHS's collection of Cass Gilbert papers and architectural drawings (PR 21), which has the architect's drawings for the bridge (under the name Kill Van Kull Bridge, not Bayonne Bridge).
Bayonne Bridge (N.J. and N.Y.); Kill Van Kull (N.J. and N.Y.); Bridges -- Design and construction.; Bridges -- New Jersey -- Bayonne.; Bridges -- New York (N.Y.) -- Staten Island.; Historic preservation.; Digital images.; Digital media.; Files (digital files)
- Collection transmittal letter with contextual information, 2021 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "The Beautiful Arch: The Bayonne Bridge Story" (1 of 2). DVD (RESTRICTED), 2020 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Documentary video about the history of the bridge. Approximately 24 minutes in length. Produced by Stokes Creative Group and Richard Grubb & Associates, Inc., 2014-2019. The DVD was retained for context and back-up and the object packaging may be viewed, but the files on the discs may not be accessed. Patrons may only use the preserved digital files from the DVD noted next.
- "The Beautiful Arch: The Bayonne Bridge Story" (2 of 2). Digital files, 2020 May 5 (Digital folder PR 443)
  Existence and Location of Copies
  All the content of the collection can be found on-line on the Port Authority's website: https://www.panynj.gov/bridges-tunnels/en/bayonne-bridge/history.html
- "The Bayonne Bridge: The Beautiful Arch" (1 of 2), DVD (RESTRICTED), 2020 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  School lesson plan for 4th grade. Prepared by Richard Grubb & Associates, 2020. The DVD was retained for context and back-up and the object packaging may be viewed, but the file on the disc may not be accessed. Patrons may only use the preserved digital file from the DVDs noted next.
- "The Bayonne Bridge: The Beautiful Arch" (2 of 2), Digital files, 2020 (Digital folder PR 443)
  One PDF of lesson plan to accompany above DVD documentary history. All the content of the collection can be found on-line on the Port Authority's website: https://www.panynj.gov/bridges-tunnels/en/bayonne-bridge/history.html
- Archival documentation (1 of 2). CD (RESTRICTED), 2020 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  From a contextual note on the DVD: "This DVD contains materials produced in 2020 as required by the Bayonne Bridge Navigational Clearance Program Programmatic Agreement. It contains historic photographs, historic engineering drawings, and booklets. The photograph folder contains 49 photographs, each 8 x 10" with a caption describing the image, the date, camera angle and source. The engineering drawings folder contains high quality scans of the original engineering drawings of the Bayonne Bridge. The booklets folder contains a digital version of three booklets documenting the construction of the Bayonne Bridge and a scan of the original bridge permit. The booklets are the first and second progress report and a report published by the American Bridge Company of its role in the bridge's construction."
  The DVD was retained for context and back-up and the object packaging may be viewed, but the file on the disc may not be accessed. Patrons may only use the preserved digital files from the DVD noted next.
- Archival documentation, 1920s-1930s (2 of 2). Digital files, 2020 (Digital folder PR 443)
- Time lapse video of bridge reconstruction, 2013-2019 (1 of 2). CD (RESTRICTED), 2021 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  The CD was retained for context and back-up and the object packaging may be viewed, but the file on the disc may not be accessed. Patrons may only use the preserved digital file from the CD noted next.
- Time lapse video of bridge reconstruction, 2013-2019 (2 of 2). Digital file, 2021 (Digital folder PR 443)
  One mp4 file, approximately 3 minutes in length. All the content of the collection can be found on-line on the Port Authority's website: https://www.panynj.gov/bridges-tunnels/en/bayonne-bridge/history.html
- Historic American Engineering Record (HAER), NJ-66 (1 of 2). CD (RESTRICTED), 2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  The CD was retained for context and back-up and the object packaging may be viewed, but the files on the disc may not be accessed. Patrons may only use the preserved digital files from the CD noted next.
- Historic American Engineering Record (HAER), NJ-66 (2 of 2). Digital files, 2014 (Digital folder PR 443)
  3 PDFs of HAER-related letters and report, with 10 photographs. All the content of the collection can be found on-line on the Port Authority's website: https://www.panynj.gov/bridges-tunnels/en/bayonne-bridge/history.html
- "Bayonne Bridge: A landmark by land, sea, and air", 2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Book by Darl Rastorfer, published by the Port Authority for the 75th anniversary of the bridge. All the content of the collection can be found on-line on the Port Authority's website: https://www.panynj.gov/bridges-tunnels/en/bayonne-bridge/history.html
- "Bayonne Bridge: The Beautiful Arch", circa 2019 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  3 copies of an information pamphlet about the bridge, the reconstruction project, and statistics. All the content of the collection can be found on-line on the Port Authority's website: https://www.panynj.gov/bridges-tunnels/en/bayonne-bridge/history.html